If you're a javascript
developer chances are
you didn't learn about
the value vs reference
you may not even know what
I'm talking about when I say that
it's one of those things that rarely
gets the attention it deserves but it's a
fundamental feature of javascript
and the source of a ton
Of bugs
for all of us
and if you knew how it works you
could save yourself a ton of time
and pain.
So what is this all about when we say
copy by value versus copied by reference why
should you care and how does this affect
you as a javascript developers weather in
your day to day job
or an interview process by the
end of this video you will master
this fundamental concept.
Welcome back
everybody this is the last episode
episode ten of this
ten part series I'm calling
Ten things javascript
developers should know
but probably don't
episode final episode ten
value vs reference plus a big announcement
at the end of the video as to what we're
going to do after the
series and spoiler alert
It involves you.
There are changes come into color code
and I can't wait to share them with you
with that
Episode ten
In episode one and two of this series we
talked a lot about inheritance
and how in javascript
Prototypes are the way we create
inheritance hierarchies.
I also showed you that everything eventually is
an instance of the object type.
The truth is
however
that there are two types of
values not just objects
primitives and objects but wait real
quick what are values again
in a variable
declaration like this
you have the
variable on the left side and
you have the value on the right side
so if you take all kinds of values in javascript
you have two kinds
you have primitives these
Which are Number, Boolean,
String, Null and Undefined
and you have
objects these once
Object, Array, Function, Date, Regex
and couple other ones, but why
do we care that they're are different well
we care because they act differently
in important ways most importantly
in the way they're stored okay so what does
that mean let's start
with a simple example
To The Browser.
Alright let's start
with the simple one
const a equals one
Const b also equal
actually lets do two
A triple equals b
False of course
makes sense
Let's do another one
where a and b are
the same
a triple equals b
True
simple stuff
Not a big deal
Now what if I do
a equals an array
That
Houses one and
same thing would be
a triple equals b
false
Now it is the easiest thing in the world to
look at this code
and say wow javascript sucks
That is a lazy
way of looking at it
Don't become one of those people
this is a cop out answer
don't cop out.
Instead we can try and understand
what is going on here I Grant you
That
There are parts of
javascript that were
decided on
and implemented decades ago and they are
truly weird and and don't make much sense
this isn't one of
those scenarios
so to explain this
one thing you'll notice is that
one of these is a primitive so
this one is a
primitive where the the two are equal
and this one they're not primitive
that are objects which are...
i mean arrays which are a type of object
So
it doesn't matter that there is a primitive
inside it what matters
is that it's an array.
So let's try
one more thing another primitive
value let's say String so
const myName equals SINAAA
Okay
So
Before we go any further
we need to understand
what this one line
does and I promise you
Most of you watching don't fully understand
this one simple line of javascript
and
Some of you
most definitely don't
know the difference
between this line and this line
myCar equals an object
Those are two
kind of similar looking
Statements but they're
are very very different
and I'm going to dissect them, I'm going
to need my trusty animation too
i don't think I can code
So I'm going to get out
of this bubble
Whoops
I'm going to use my trusty animation board.
When you assign a
value to variable like this
Javascript does one of two things depending
on the value that's on the right side
This being the value
If it's a primitive say a string
javascript takes the actual
value of the string
and points the variable to that
it doesn't create a new string
and that is key here on the other hand
if it's not a primitive let's say it's an
object javascript actually creates the
object from scratch and points the variable
to the location not the object itself
but the location of the object in your
computer's memory aka
The address aka it's reference
oh but wait a minute
that's not what happens with strings
If you don't create
a string then where
does this come from
Well good question Craig
you can think of
primitives as
Values that already exist in memory it's a
totally different way of thinking about it
and I know it's it's a little
it's a little more complicated than
that because obviously javascript
can't have of all the possible
numbers and strings in the world
in its memory but for the purpose of the
value assignment primitives or what they are
the value itself it's that simple
what you see is what you get.
Let's go back to the
browser real quick
I'm going to try one more
thing const a equals one
Okay and const b equals
one same exact thing
a and b literally have the same
value of one
They don't have a copy of one that's
the important part here whereas if I have
while I can create objects
now if I have to to empty objects
a and b have totally different values even
though they look alike
one is always one
but an empty object isn't necessarily the
same thing as another empty object
They're like twins identical
but separate people
Now back to the original example
Right when we do the triple equals
one is always one
javascript looks at that and says
True they are the same thing
whereas if I use
a non primitive so let's say I use
An array that was the
example we had before
a triple equals b is going to be false
so now hopefully you know
what is going on here
An array with the number one inside
of it is not the same thing
as another array
with a number one in it
think about maybe
The first array is my favorite
Single digit number
And maybe the second
one is the number of
times I have fallen
down the stairs this week
also one
so they're representing
two very different facts
Whereas one again is always one
or let's use an object
this time
const
Umm..
a equals
skills
Or skill.
Let's say we're representing two
different people skill cooking
That's person a
Person b
might also
Have a skill of cooking so maybe a is
representing someone like Gordon Ramsey who does
cooks food
And
Be person b's representing someone
like Walter white who also cooks
but...
he's a different person
and it's a different kind
of cook
Right
so
again the objects look
identical
but there are representing very different
kind of cooking and very different people
although similar in some ways too
So if I can compare them javascript goes
no no no these are two different people
and that's where we get with objects
So to recap primitives are are assigned by
value
and those are Numbers, Strings,
Booleans, Null and Undefined.
Objects on the other hand get assigned
by reference and those are
Objects, Arrays, Functions, Dates and Regex
So now what, what do I
do with this information right
I'm going to show you some real world
examples where this actually matters
so first one is comparison
where we looked at it
but a lot of times
we need to check
the values against each other
a very common thing to do in
any programming language
and pretty much any
Application so your
app is a alarm clock
app and you want to check the time and
see as soon as it hits seven A.M you want
to sound the alarm
it's very simple concept right
Seven is just a number you might have
something like this
actually in javascript we check the current
Time of day
and as long as it matches seven
You can do a triple equals and and that's
it, you're done this is basically all you
have to do when you compare those two
numbers vs say this is something I had to
go through recently
so you have a profile page
and you want to
enable and disable
The save button based on whether or not the
user has updated the profile right so we
wanted to be disabled at first
but as soon as the user
changes anything on their profile
You want to enable the
button and then allow them to
to click on it
If you simply compare the original object
if you compare that object with the object
that the form is giving you
they will always be different because
even though they might look alike to you.
They are different
objects in memory so
A comparison will always
well return false which means there
are always going to be different objects
so you're enable or your save
button is always going to be enable
another scenario that I can think
of is when you pass a variable
to a function and you want that function to
perform an operation on on that parameter
Actually I'm going
to show you this
in the browser
Say I have a function
that says function
Increment
Age
Right and I pass in it
An age to it
And I want the
function to take the age
Equals age plus one
Right so an increment my age
If I simply say const
my age equals
Ten
Ten years old
And I'm going to call the function
increment age and passing my age
What do we think is going
to happen while we think
That it took the
Guess
just
So
This my age we are passing it into this
function and we think that age is going to be
age plus one
So I think my age
should now be eleven
But if I look at my age
It's still ten
Now why is that while the
value of the age variable
is a number so it's a primitive
Now so when you pass it to a function
you're actually passing the value of ten
Not the variable itself
not the age itself
So
It gets copied by
value not reference
Whereas if I have a function
That
takes instead of increment
Increment age same thing
but it actually takes an object so
let's say we're passing the entire user
and the user object has a
Age
Property on it
user.age plus one I
know I can do a shorthand but
We're simplifying
If I now have const me
equals this object that has
age in it
Ten
Twelve ten
And let's say I do increment
Increment age
And I pass in
Not user
me
Right
What do we think is going to
happen well i'm passing this
Object type not a primitive, a non
primitive we're passing it to this object
Is going to get passed in as reference so
the actual me object itself is going to go
in here
and the age of
that object which is the
me object is going to be
manipulated so let's see.
How that works
me
Now age is eleven
right
so
again that's because
object are passed as reference
so when I call increment
age and passing by object
actually passing the reference itself
which by the way may or
may not be what you want
this is a really
is important thing
and as a side note this might
seem like a good idea now because we're like
oh well we're manipulating the right object
in functional programming we call this
as side effects right
this is most of you probably know this but
That means the function effects variables
that are outside its own context meaning
this me object which
does not belong
In the scope of this function
It gets affected by the by the function
which is a big no-no in functional
programming with the concept of pure
functions is that they don't change variable
it's outside
the scope of themselves
they create a new variable
and return that new
variable back to you
But that's a lesson
for another day
Water break
Lark.
So as you can see
There are real world consequences
to understanding value vs reference
right and that could be
the cause of a lot of your bugs
When you understand
how values are set
and
passed around
You can catch those bugs a lot faster
and avoid making mistakes again
So that was comparison
I also want to cover copying
so let's go back to the browser
for one last time
To The Browser
So whenever when you
you assign a value
const a equals
One
right some I'm going to
do this and then instead of
assigning a number to b
I'm going to assign b to a
Okay so now we're talking about
How the values get copied
So if I'm referencing a
And pointing b to a
Right
what is a
a is one and be is one
right
if I change a
it eight
Whoops
const a they don't
They can't change
let a
Browser
and let b right a is one
be is one so if I
Set a to
The number seven
What do you think it's
going to happen to b
Let's take a look
Be say there's one
right
but
because again we copied the value we didn't
b was not pointing to a
b was pointing to one
So if I change a
b is not affected whereas if I
use an object
Instead and say a's name is
Sina
And now I'm going to
Point b to a right
What is a
a is Sina
b is Sina
now what if I change
the name of a
To Qoli
Right
a is Qoli
what is b
b is also Qoli
Right so why is that
again because it
it copies be is pointing to the reference
of the object because it's not a primitive
So uh and even more interesting
than that is when I assign
a to something
totally different
name equals CRAIG
Right so what is a
a is CRAIG
So would you say
be is also Craig
No b stayed the same because
b was not pointing to a
b was pointing to were
This
Qoli
Object was in memory
it has nothing to do
with a, the fact that
a changed and
that affected b was
indirectly it was affecting each other
they were affecting each other
and that means that
if either of them not just a
Would be updated the other one would also
see the the change but this is an entirely
different assignment
so just
to takes a out of the game and a
is not pointing to that original object
Anymore
Okay so hopefully
that was clear
You have to go play with this stuff and and
make sure you understand it for yourself
you can come back
and watch this again
A second time it will make
a lot more sense hopefully
I'll promise you you'll get it
things
like this come up a lot
in javascript interviews
so this is definitely a good one to know
and with that my friends we have reached the
end of
the series but wait
a minute what's next
is this all well i'm
glad you asked
Qoli.
If you followed the series
first of all i wanna say thank you
I hope you found it useful
but this is not where this
javascript journey ends
Obviously there's
a lot more to learn
in javascript than the
ten things I taught you
and if you follow the
the whole playlist
Awesome
So here's
what I'm going to do next
I'm going to continue
with ten more concepts
But I want them to come from you
I'm going to look for comments on any
of the videos in the series the ten videos
leave a comment and
tell me what specifically
about javascript
a Javascript concept
You want to learn that you've
had a hard time understanding
It has to be a fundamental
can't be some framework or
or something super niche that's
all I'm asking for
Right you can ask anything
else as long as it's a fundamental
I will even mention
you by name
and send you a beautiful color code sticker
like this no matter where you live in the
world for free as long as I can
Ship to your country
All you gotta do is suggest what
you want to see for episode eleven
And now for the
big announcement
I have decided to create a full
javascript course
For anyone
who is looking
to get their first
or next
javascript
programming job
I've spent years putting
this thing together
and finally with
the help of my team
is coming to life
It will include
JavaScript Fundamentals
Using the why method
something I call the why method
i've used this a lot in this series
so if you like the way I'm teaching
These ten videos
that's the way it's going
to be for the full course
Interview preparation
I get this asked a lot
common mistakes that
people make during interviews
and you can easily avoid them so there's
going to be an Interview Prep section
In the course
Mastery mindset this is something that very
few people talk about something that you
can learn
and use it
to go and learn
any other language
doesn't have to stop with javascript
again using the why the method
and one of my favorite parts of this is
what I call expert conversations where I
have picked
Some of my friends
are some of the more
I guess famous youtubers and
teachers from from Twitter YouTube or
Frontend masters and
And Udemy and few other
places i've decided to talk to them
and record those conversations
Hours of expert advice on
how to nail the language
of javascript specifically
No matter what your goal
is whether you want to get
a job or you want to get a
better job you want
to make more money
You want to
Just simply become the expert in javascript
still the world's most
Popular programming language
not a bad thing to nail right
So if you want to know when the course is
released I will be announcing it on this
channel so make sure you
Subscribe or go to colorcode.io
and sign up for early
access there's a form there
I do not
send you marketing
emails or any bullsh*t like that
It's simply
a way for me to let you know
when the course is available
JavaScrip Mastery and with that again
I want to say thank you for watching the
series it's been a lot
of fun for me to seeing
your reactions and it's
just been such a positive
Experience on YouTube
YouTube is notorious for having
Really nasty comments and people
fighting I haven't seen any of that
in the series so that's
been truly amazing
to see
and this is been ten things
javascript developers should know
but probably don't
I'm looking forward to hearing what
you want to see for episode eleven
Now go write some code and I'm looking
forward to sharing my full course with you
very soon
Salute.